Qingqing Cao

☑: qicao@cs.stonybrook.edu in: linkedin.com/in/qqcao : awk.ai

EDUCATION

Stony Brook University

Aug. 2015 - May 2021 (expected)

Ph.D. in Computer Science

Wuhan University

Sept. 2011 - June 2015

B.Eng. in Computer Science & Tech

HIGHLIGHTS

I have 3+ years of research experience in **natural language processing**, **mobile computing**, and **machine learning systems**. I have focused on building efficient and practical NLP systems for both edge devices and the cloud, such as on-device question answering (MobiSys 2019), faster Transformer models (ACL 2020), and accurate energy estimation of NLP models.

EXPERIENCE

Research Assistant @ Stony Brook University, US

Jun. 2016 - Present

Advisors: Prof. Aruna Balasubramanian & Prof. Niranjan Balasubramanian

Research Intern @ Microsoft Research Redmond, US

Jun. 2018 - Aug. 2018

Mentor: Oriana Riva Topic: dynamic business web queries

Research Intern @ Bell Labs Cambridge, UK

Jul. 2017 - Sept. 2017

Mentor: Nicholas Lane Topic: mobile deep learning accelerators

PUBLICATIONS

1. [SustaiNLP@EMNLP 2020] Qingqing Cao, Harsh Trivedi, Aruna Balasubramanian, Niranjan Balasubramanian, "Towards Accurate and Reliable Energy Measurement of NLP Models". Paper: https://awk.ai/assets/sustainlp.pdf

Summary: Accurate energy measurement is critical for choosing and training large NLP models and deploying to battery-powered mobile devices. Existing utilization-based software methods do not address issues like power lag, tail energy issues. Non-utilization behaviors such as data movement in GPUs also cause energy. Resource profiling should avoid high overhead. I use a hardware power meter to measure energy accurately and quantify the error (>20%) of existing software measurements. I find current software measurements without calibration are inaccurate and cause misleading design choices.

2. [ACL 2020] Qingqing Cao, Harsh Trivedi, Aruna Balasubramanian, Niranjan Balasubramanian, "DeFormer: Decomposing Pre-trained Transformers for Faster Question Answering". Paper: https://awk.ai/assets/deformer.pdf

Summary: Pre-training large Transformers is expensive and the inference in them is prohibitively slow. I design DeFormer that decomposes pre-trained Transformers to enable faster inference for QA without repeating the pre-training. DeFormer achieves >3.1x speedup inference speedup and >65% memory reduction with minimal (\sim 1%) accuracy loss.

3. [MobiSys 2019] Qingqing Cao, Niranjan Balasubramanian, Aruna Balasubramanian, "DeQA: On-device Question Answering". Paper: https://awk.ai/assets/deqa.pdf

Summary: DeQA is an on-device question answering system to help mobile users find information more efficiently without privacy issues. Deep learning-based QA models are slow and unusable on mobile. I design the latency- and memory- optimizations for the QA models to run locally on mobile devices. DeQA effectively reduces the memory footprint and improves the QA latency $6 \sim 13x$ with minimal accuracy drop (< 1%).

- 4. [EMDL@MobiSys 2017] Qingqing Cao, Niranjan Balasubramanian, Aruna Balasubramanian, "MobiRNN: Efficient Recurrent Neural Network Execution on Mobile GPU" Paper: https://awk.ai/assets/mobirnn.pdf
 - Summary: MobiRNN is a mobile specific optimization library for RNNs that focuses on offloading deep learning tasks to the mobile GPU.
- 5. [MobiCom 2017] Jian Xu (co-primary), Qingqing Cao (co-primary), Aditya Prakash, Aruna Balasubramanian, and Don Porter. "UIWear: Easily Adapting User Interfaces for Wearable Devices". Paper: https://awk.ai/assets/uiwear.pdf
- 6. [MobiCom 2017 demo] Jian Xu (co-primary), Qingqing Cao (co-primary), Aditya Prakash, Aruna Balasubramanian, and Don Porter. "UIWear: Easily Adapting User Interfaces for Wearable Devices". Demo video: https://youtu.be/YEQ3HNeQnts

AWARDS

MobiSys 2017 Student Travel Grant	2017
Special CS Department Chair Fellowship	2015
Meritorious Winner in the Mathematical Contest in Modeling (MCM)	2014

SERVICE

Program Committee: NAACL 2021, Eurosys 2021 (shadow), ACL 2020 (demo), MobiSys 2018 (PhD forum), IEEE Transactions on Mobile Computing (reviewer).

Secondary Reviewer: EMNLP 2020, IMC 2017, EuroSys 2019, MobiSys 2017 \sim 2020, MobiCom 2019 \sim 2021, SIGCOMM 2019 \sim 2020.

Volunteering Service: Student volunteer for MobiSys 2017 and ACL 2020, mentor for Stony Brook CS Grad Buddies Program.

SKILLS

Programming: Python, C, Java.

Machine Learning: TensorFlow, PyTorch, Scikit-learn, Numpy, XGBoost.

Courses

Computer Systems: Analysis of Algorithms (CSE548), Operating Systems (CSE506), Fundamentals of Computer Networks (CSE534).

Machine Learning: Machine Learning (CSE512), Artificial Intelligence (CSE537).